Who's there?
It's Mui.
Ah, Mui...
I'll open the door.
You can come in.
Follow me.
THE SMELL OF THE GREEN PAPAYA
It's little Mui,
our new servant girl.
Poor thing, she walked
a whole day to get here.
If To was still alive,
they'd be the same age.
Let's not talk about that...
Perhaps she's better off
where she is now.
It's the curfew soon
and Trung isn't back yet.
Mother's going to bed.
I'll go up and help her.
Ah, Trung...
Aren't you in bed yet, father?
Go back to sleep.
The mistress said so.
I'll wake you to make the fire.
Remember... For this dish,
the oil has to be hot.
Fry the vegetable.
Burn it for flavour.
Not too much or it gets all soft.
Then you put it aside.
You do the same with the meat.
Put that in the water.
Fat make the boiled vegetable shine.
It looks nicer.
Whether it looks nice or not,
we eat it.
But the masters are different.
Once it's cooked...
Then share it between 2 plates.
Don't forget to keep some for us.
There, grandmother
has finished her prayers.
Put the vegetables in the water.
Whose mother is she?
The master's. Wash your hands.
She lost her husband
just after the master was born.
Now, she spends
all her time praying.
Quick, put some rice in a big bowl.
Is it all ready?
Yes, it's ready.
Mui, take grandmother's tray.
It's alright, I'll take it.
Take this one then.
Father, I'm eating out
with Khuyen.
Have your nap as usual.
We'll be back for tea.
And me, can l?
No, you're too little.
Mui, go and get some more soup.
Mother would like you
to keep her company during meals.
I'm going up too!
Take this upstairs.
Eat up. You're going to be late.
No classes now, grandmother.
It's summer holidays.
Ah yes, that's right...
We're going, mum.
Khuyen and l
will be back for tea.
Alright, I'll buy cakes.
Good-bye, madam.
Good-bye.
Mui, you can eat now.
Lam, eat up, dear.
Enjoy the meal, mum.
Here's your bowl. Eat.
There's no soup left.
What a nuisance.
Upstairs or downstairs,
we spread it out and have none left.
After, wash the dishes.
Who was that man with Mr Trung?
That's Mr Khuyen,
Mr Trung's friend. Eat up.
Tin!
Thank you. Good-bye.
Good-bye.
Mui, wash your hands
and go to buy 10 cakes.
In 3 months, you'll go home
to visit your mother.
Thank you, madam.
Mui, hurry up. It's almost time
to light the fire.
Little girl...
Your name?
I'm called Mui.
I see... You're Mui...
My name is Thuan.
It's almost time for prayers.
Is grandmother well?
Yes, she's well.
That's very good then!
Very good!
Thank you, little Mui.
Good-bye...
Good-bye, Mr Thuan.
Where are you going?
For some fresh air.
Yes, in this heat,
it's hard to sleep.
Watch out for the curfew.
What heat...
My God, what heat...
It's alright...
You can put your things away
tomorrow.
You've worked enough today.
Get some rest.
Where are your parents?
Do you have brothers or sisters?
My father died three years ago.
My mother and my sister
are still in my village.
Will you go to see them soon?
The mistress said in three months,
I'll see my mother again.
That's good. The mistress is kind.
Before, who slept on this bed?
A servant like you and me.
She went home to get married.
Is the photo on the altar
the grandmother's husband?
Yes.
When he died,
he was still young.
Who's the little girl?
It's a sad story.
She was the masters' daughter.
Her name was To.
She died seven years ago.
If she was still alive,
you'd be the same age.
How did she die?
A disease.
But the master thinks
it's his fault.
Why?
Seven years ago,
the master left the house
with all the family's money.
It was the third time
he'd done that.
Before, when he'd spent it all,
he came back.
But that time,
he was away longer than usual.
But the other times,
when he came back,
she didn't say anything?
Nothing. Not a single word.
She was happy.
She cried for joy.
What about To then?
The curfew...
There, a little fresh air.
The master must be back by now.
Three weeks after he left,
To fell ill.
And the day before he returned,
she died.
He must have thought she died
to atone for the sins
he had committed.
That's why he never leaves
the house anymore.
Right, let's sleep...
Tomorrow, we have to be up early.
Mother...
Get up. It's time.
You're lucky.
At your age,
you still have sweet dreams.
What did you dream about?
I don't know...
My God...
I'd like to dream.
But I haven't dreamed for ages.
Let's go and wash.
Some mornings,
I wake up with the image
of an old woman in my mind.
Perhaps it's because
I dreamed at night.
But I don't know if the old woman
is my mother
or if she's me.
My God, who's in the kitchen
this early?
Mistress, are you already up?
Any rice left?
Just enough for 4 or 5 days.
This is for the market.
Make sure there's enough to eat
for a few days.
See these earrings?
The master has left
with all the money again. My God!
Let's go and clean our teeth,
wash our faces,
hands and feet.
Then comb our hair.
And don't forget the toilet.
No, not that one either.
I'm sorry...
It's alright. Good-bye.
Good-bye.
What's wrong?
I had a fight.
Who with?
The children.
Did they hurt you?
Is daddy home?
No. Go and ask Mui
for some clean clothes.
When there's not enough,
use a lot of salt.
That way,
they'll eat more rice
with the dishes.
For the boiled vegetables.
Take this upstairs.
Mother said to start.
Ugh! It's too salty!
Look.
Eat.
Is it good?
Little Mui... Come here.
I want to ask you something.
Thank you, Mr Thuan.
Is grandmother well?
We're almost out of rice.
We haven't sold a yard of cloth.
Two reels of cotton...
What can we buy with the money
from two reels?
My God...
It's your fault.
If you'd known how to love him,
he wouldn't have left
with other women.
I knew from the start:
my son would be unhappy with you.
You have a husband
and you don't know
how to make him happy.
Alright, that's enough.
What about the rest of the papaya?
Throw it away.
Enough!
Take this up.
It's alright.
You can go and eat.
Enjoy it, mother.
When will daddy be back?
I don't know... Eat.
Why are you crying like that?
Why doesn't daddy come home?
Shut up!
Thank you.
My pleasure. Good-bye.
Good-bye.
That's it, money for rice.
Go and buy 25 kg of rice.
Hurry. We have to cut the meat.
There... Put that there.
It's very good rice!
- We have a guest tonight.
- Who?
Mr Khuyen.
Who's Mr Khuyen?
Mr Trung's friend, of course!
Can I fry the vegetables
on my own?
Yes, if you want.
Three years after grandfather died,
she still loved her husband
and refused to marry me.
Since that day, I've watched her
from a distance.
She's moved house several times
and I've always followed her.
That's how we were able to meet,
you and l.
Since To's death,
grandmother hasn't been downstairs.
I haven't seen her
for seven years now.
Tell me, little Mui,
couldn't you get her down
into the yard
so that I can see her?
Why don't you go to see her?
If you hid, she wouldn't see you.
No, that's not possible.
If she saw me,
it would be terrible.
No, it's not possible.
Go on, go up!
It doesn't matter.
My God!
The mistress is fond
of these vases.
They're very old antiques.
All my savings
wouldn't be enough to buy one.
You're lucky.
Mistress, wake up, quickly!
A very valuable piece
but without its twin,
it's worth next to nothing....
It's up to you.
Alright, I accept.
Trung, quick!
10 YEARS LATER
Mui!
Hurry!
My mother wants to see you.
For some time now,
business has been slack.
If it goes on like this,
we'll have problems.
The inner yard isn't used
for anything.
We should have
another parrot farm.
Yes... We'll see...
In that case, I'll ask around.
Mother's talking to Mui right now.
Mui won't be that badly off
with your friend Khuyen.
He lives alone
and writes music...
His parents are rich.
She'll be better paid
than she is here.
I would have given these to To
if she were alive.
Without knowing it,
you've always been a great comfort.
Thanks to you,
I feel I've had a daughter.
Lam has left.
He needs somewhere to write.
Now, you're the one who's leaving.
For a long time,
I hoped Lam would take you
as his wife.
My daughter... my little daughter!
Don't eat!
Take me to a restaurant.
Have you got a lot done?
Play me what you've written.
That smells good.
How's your new servant?
Alright.
What does that mean, "alright"?
She works hard...
I'm not asking you that.
But it doesn't matter.
Where's the vase I gave you?
It's broken.
Broken?
You mean: "She broke it"!
If I say she did it on purpose,
what would your answer be?
I wonder what percentage
of women in Vietnam
have never touched
their fiance's head.
My mother told me that before
they used to teach girls
that a well-educated woman
should never do it.
She also said
that it's almost two weeks
since you last came to see us.
Your father's surprised too.
In... my... garden...
there's... a... papaya... tree...
The papaya...
hang... in bunches...
The ripe papaya...
have a pale yellow colour.
The ri... The ripe papaya...
are sweet with a sugary taste.
We've been raising a black dog
for three years now.
His body is long.
He has big feet.
He has big feet
and big ears.
I'll start, okay?
The spring water,
nestled in a hole in a rock,
shimmers softly when disturbed.
The vibrations of the ground
have given birth to strong waves
which crash together
in an irregular swell
on the surface,
without cresting.
If there 's a verb
meaning "to move harmoniously"
it must be used here.
The cherry trees,
gripped in shadows,
spread out and curl up,
sway and twist,
to the rhythm of the water.
But the interesting thing
is that...
however much they change,
they keep the shape
of a cherry tree.